Finding Aid for the Robert Wheeler Rand Collection Biomed.0402
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Professional Materials., 1955-2000; Series 2.; 103 folders (4500 35mm slides), 51 glass slides, 4 objects, 5 films, 3 tapes, 2 cartons instruments
  - Slides., 1967-2000; Subseries 3.; 74 folders with ca. 4500 35mm slides; 1 box with 51 glass lantern slides; more slides in RESTRICTED
    - Superconducting magnet., 1970; 35 mm slides (Box 3, Folder 10)
      19 slides, views of equipment
    - NMR (Nuclear Magnetic Resonance) Centers, Inc., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 3, Folder 11)
      21 text slides, marketing the idea of freestanding NMR centers; 3 title slides for Robert W. Rand Medical Corporation
    - Neurosurgical operations on identified tumors, etc., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Osteochondroma, 4 slides; meningioma, 2 slides; brain stem tumor, 1 slide; hemifacial spasm, 2 slides; vestibular nerves, 1 slide; cerebellar stimulation implant, 1 slide
    - Surgical operations and dissections, unidentified., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 3, Folder 13)
      ca. 180 slides
    - Surgical operations and dissections, unidentified., 1976-1980; 35 mm slides (Box 3, Folder 14)
      ca. 120 slides
    - Miscellaneous texts., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 3, Folder 15)
      types of neurosurgery, 5 slides; diagnosis of stroke syndrome, 3 slides
    - Miscellaneous unidentified images., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 3, Folder 16)
      ca. 35 slides
    - Miscellaneous unidentified equipment., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 3, Folder 17)
      18 slides
    - "Randy Whittell - 'Bob's Presentation' "., 1991 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Four 35mm slides and one 3.5 inch floppy disk.
      Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
    - Glass lantern slides., undated; 3 x 4 " (Box 7)
      51 slides, some labeled; 21 of the slides came from a container labeled "Carl W. Rand"
  - Photographs., 1968-1985; Subseries 4.; 6 folders
    Contains both positives and negatives
    - Brain visualizations., 1978, undated; 5 x 7" positives and negatives (Box 3, Folder 19)
      12 photographs, 10 negatives
    - Brain visualizations., undated; 4 x 5" negatives (Box 3, Folder 20)
      13 negatives
    - Mouse kidney., undated; 5 x 7", 8 x 10" black & white (Box 3, Folder 21)
      views of operation, tissue sections, animal before and after
    - Illustrations from "Microneurosurgery"., 1985; 7.5 x 7.5" black & white (Box 3, Folder 22)
      copies of figures from Ch.5: Microsurgical neuroanatomy, Ch.38: Trigeminal neuralgia, Ch.39: Hemifacial spasm
    - Frontispiece from "Cryosurgery"., 1968; 8 x 10" color (Box 3, Folder 23)
      "Cryosurgery", ed. by Robert W. Rand, et al. Charles C Thomas
    - Head holder., undated; 4 x 6" color (Box 3, Folder 24)
      19 photographs of an adjustable head holder attached to an operating table
  - Films and Magnetic Tapes., 1976; Subseries 5.; 5 films, 3 tapes; more films in RESTRICTED
    Two of the films were not authored by Dr. Rand
    - "Percutaneous Radiofrequency Cervical Cordotomy", by Hubert L. Rosomoff, Department of Neurological Surgery, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, Yeshiva University, N.Y., undated; 16 mm, color R film with sound, 9" reel (Box 5, Folder Film 1)
      hand-written header note added: V.A. Hospital
      the original container bore label of Pittsburgh Motion Picture Lab.
    - "Microsurgery of the canine common bile duct", by Robert W. Rand, Jack A. Cannon, Rafael S. Rodriguez., undated; 16 mm, color film, 10.5" reel (Box 5, Folder Film 2)
    - "Microsurgery of Stroke; STA-MCA Anastomosis", by Albert L. Rhoton, University of Florida, Gainesville., 1976 April 20; 16 mm, color film, 10.5" reel (Box 5, Folder Film 3)
      original container bore Dr. Rhoton's business card, with Dr. Rand's note "OK, 1977 AANS"
    - "Cryosurgery of the pituitary", by Robert W. Rand, Frank J. Morlino, David H. Solomon, in cooperation with the Neuroendocrine Research Clinic, School of Medicine, UCLA., uindated; 16 mm, color film with sound, 12" reel (Box 8, Folder Film 4)
      "This medical teaching film is supported in part with a grant from Pfizer Laboratories. Product of Academic Communications Facility, UCLA".
    - Untitled film., undated; 35 mm, black & white, 3.5" reel (Box 3, Folder Film 5)
    - Untitled tape., undated; 1 Memorex 6250 BPI magentic tape, 10.5" reel (Box 8, Folder Tape 1)
      label bears annotation: "0001. Echeverra 30392/ original control run for Dr. Rand"
    - Untitled tape., undated; 1 BASF 6250 BPI magentic tape, 10.5" reel (Box 8, Folder Tape 2)
      label says: "Dr. Rand/survey contrast & high resolution scans/Run 30345, Run 30346/1.5 mm"
    - Untitled tape., undated; 1 Memorex 6250 BPI magentic tape, 10.5" reel (Box 8, Folder Tape 3)
      the reel bears two small stickers with numbers 10-6-0, 10-30-0, and 11-14-0, and an identity label saying RAND 3
  - Restricted Materials., Series 6.; 25 folders with ca. 35 mm 670 slides, 8 films, 63 glass lantern slides
    - Slides., Subseries 1.; 24 folders with ca. 670 35 mm slides, box with 63 glass lantern slides
      Some lantern slides originated from Dr. Carl Rand. 35 mm slides are arranged by disease when there are multiple patients, and alphabetically by patients' names when the disease is unidentified or concerns only one or two patients
      - Acoustic tumors., 1976-1984; 35 mm slides (Box 11, Folder 1)
        70 slides, 21 named patients
        restricted for patient confidentiality
      - Acoustic tumors., 7.5 x 20 cm glass lantern slide (Box 9)
        3 glass lantern slides, 1 patient, acoustic neuroma
      - Arterio-venous malformations., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 11, Folder 2)
        6 slides, three named patients
      - Arterio-venous malformations., undated; 7.5 x 20 cm glass lantern slide (Box 9)
        1 slide, 1 patient
      - Epilepsy., 1956-1968; 35 mm slides (Box 11, Folder 3)
        26 slides, 10 named patients
      - Epilepsy., undated; 7.5 x 20 cm glass lantern slides (Box 9)
        22 slides, 1 patient
      - Gamma knife., 1983, 1992; 35 mm slides (Box 11, Folder 4)
        6 slides, 4 named patients
      - Infusion therapy., 1997-1998; 35 mm slides (Box 11, Folder 5)
        40 slides, 5 named patients
      - Orbital tumors., 1970, 1976; 35 mm slides (Box 11, Folder 6)
        7 slides, 2 named patients
      - Parkinsonism., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 11, Folder 7)
        43 slides, 2 named patients
      - Pituitary tumors, chromophobes., 1976, 1984; 35 mm slides (Box 11, Folder 8)
        21 slides, 10 named patients
      - Pituitary tumor., undated; 7.5 x 20 cm glass lantern slide (Box 9)
      - Spinal cord., 1972-1979; 35 mm slides (Box 11, Folder 9)
        46 slides, 7 named patients
      - Spinal injury., undated; 7.5 x 20 cm glass lantern slide (Box 9)
      - Tic douloureux., 1992; 35 mm slides (Box 11, Folder 10)
        39 slides, 10 named patients
      - Unnamed patients., undated; 35 mm slides, photographs and negatives (Box 11, Folder 11)
        43 35 mm slides showing faces and bodies; multiple photographs with negatives of one patient
      - Unnamed patients., undated; 7.5 x 20 cm glass lantern slides (Box 9)
        4 slides, 4 patients; whole body and faces
      - Patient names A, B - various conditions., 1971-1992; 35 mm slides (Box 11, Folder 12)
        30 slides, 11 patients, including meningioma, kidney disease, empty sella, glioblastoma
      - Patient names C, D, E - various conditions., 1980-1993; 35 mm slides (Box 11, Folder 13)
        9 35 mm slides, 8 patients, including arachnoiditis, depressed fracture, mycrocele fragments, cholesteatoma, cerebral aneurysm
      - Patient names C, D - various conditions., 7.5 x 20 cm glass lantern slides (Box 9)
        5 glass lantern slides, 1 patient
      - Patient names F - various conditions., 35 mm slides; 1972, 1979, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 14)
        18 slides, 3 patients
      - Patient names F - various conditions., 7.5 x 20 cm glass lantern slides (Box 9)
        4 slides, 2 patients
      - Patient names G - various conditions., 1956, 1975; 35 mm slides (Box 11, Folder 15)
        18 35 mm slides, 7 patients, including low grade glioma, 3d ventricle tumor
      - Patient names G - various conditions., 7.5 x 20 cm glass lantern slides (Box 9)
        2 glass lantern slides, 1 patient, acromegali
      - Patient names H - various conditions., 1972, 1978, 1980; 35 mm slides (Box 11, Folder 16)
        22 slides, 5 patients, including temporal focal microgliosis, diastamatamyelia
      - Patient names J, K, L - various conditions., undated, 1992; 35 mm slides (Box 11, Folder 17)
        28 35 mm slides, 7 patients, including right frontal astrocytoma, aneurysms
      - Patient names K, L - various conditions., 7.5 x 20 cm glass lantern slides (Box 9)
        3 glass lantern slides, 3 patients, stereotaxic implant, cerebellar tremor, bilateral subdural hematoma
      - Patient names M - various conditions., 1964-1991; 35 mm slides (Box 11, Folder 18)
        32 35 mm slides, 7 patients, including Nelson's syndrome, basilar artery aneurism, carotid-cavernous fistula
      - Patient names M - various conditions., 7.5 x 20 cm glass lantern slide (Box 9)
        5 glass lantern slides, 5 patients, astrocytoma, thalamic stimulation, cingulte seizures
      - Patient names N, O - various conditions., undated; 35 mm slides (Box 11, Folder 19)
        33 35 mm slides, 4 patients, including syringomyelia, post fossa meningioma
      - Patient names N, O - various conditions., 7.5 x 20 cm glass lantern slides (Box 9)
        4 glass lantern slides, 3 patients, meningioma
      - Patient names P - various conditions., 1965, undated; 35 mm slides (Box 11, Folder 20)
        30 35 mm slides, 6 patients, hemangioma, venous angioma, motor cortex, Arnold-Chiari malformation
      - Patient names P - various conditions., 7.5 x 20 cm glass lantern slide (Box 9)
        1 glass slide, 1 patient, thalamic stimulation
      - Patient names R - various conditions., 1980; 35 mm slides (Box 11, Folder 21)
        9 slides, 3 patients
      - Patient names S - various conditions., 1979; 35 mm slides (Box 11, Folder 22)
        35 35 mm slides, 7 patients, including glioblastoma
      - Patient names S - various conditions., 7.5 x 20 cm glass lantern slides (Box 10)
        5 glass lantern slides, 4 patients, craniophyaryngioma, astrocytoma, anterior choroidal artery
      - Patient names T - various conditions., 1976, 1980; 35 mm slides (Box 11, Folder 23)
        25 slides, 5 patients, including hematoma, hemangiopericytoma
      - Patient names V, W - various conditions., 1975, 1984, 1993; 35 mm slides (Box 11, Folder 24)
        32 35 mm slides, 9 patients, including crano-synostosis, aneurysms, astrocytoma, unspecified operation
      - Patient names W - various conditions., 7.5 x 20 cm glass lantern slide (Box 10)
        1 glass lantern slide, 1 patient, chemopallidectomy
      - Unlabeled glass lantern slides., undated; 7.5 x 20 cm glass lantern slides (Box 10)
        4 slides of patients
    - Patient File., Subseries 2.; 1 folders
      Minimal correspondence concerning a patient's legal case
      - Neurological consultation on arteriovenous malformation case., 1979-1980 (Box 11, Folder 25)
        office note by RWR; correspondence; consultation and operation notes by other physicians; x-rays
    - Films., 1954-1966; Subseries 3.
      Scope and Contents
      8 films
      - Parkinsonism - Patient 1, by Drs. Rand and [Eugene] Stern., 1954 September 15; 16 mm, black and white, two 3.5" reels (Box 12, Folder Film 6)
        Veterans Administration, Sawtelle [Los Angeles]; restricted for patient confidentiality
      - Parkinsonism - Patient 2., undated; 16 mm, color, 3.75" reel (Box 12, Folder Film 7)
        brain sections, x-rays
      - Parkinsonism - Patient 3., undated; 16 mm, color, 3.75" reel (Box 12, Folder Film 8)
      - Untitled., undated; 16 mm, color, 5" reel (Box 12, Folder Film 9)
        Patient X - "pre"; Patient Y - "pre"; "slide of biopsy"
      - Untitled., undated; 16 mm, color, 2 reels, 4.5", 5.5" (Box 12, Folder Film 10)
        adult male, difficulty with movement
      - Dystonia., 1965 June 8, July 2; 16 mm, color, three 3.5" reels (Box 12, Folder Film 11)
        Academic Communications Facility, UCLA; restricted for patient confidentiality
      - Acoustic tumor., undated; 16 mm, color, two reels, 5", 5.5" (Box 12, Folder Film12)
        surgical exposure
      - Angioma of the spinal cord., 1966 November 17; 16 mm, color, 4" reel (Box 12, Folder Film13)
- Patents, Commercial Activities., 1987-2004; Series 3.; 12 folders
  Business plans, marketing plans, patents, legal and financial correspondence relating to Dr. Rand's clinical innovations
  - Malcolm-Rand Microneurosurgical Cranio-Xray Frame (TM)., 1987 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    510(K) submission to Food and Drug Administration of intention to manufacture and market; includes: I. Product specifications/product drawings. II. Testing information. III. Labeling and packaging. IV. Product equivalency, feature comparisons. V. References
  - Nova Therapeutic Systems, Inc. The Cobalt Scalpel (TM)., 1996 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    510(K) submission to Food and Drug Administration of intention to manufacture and market; includes: Nova Therapeutic System Principles [sic] and Advisory Board; Device summary; Labels for "The Cobalt Scalpel"; Licensing package with installation and operation manual; Quality assurance manual; Radiological control manual; Standard shop procedures
  - Nova Therapeutic Systems Inc. Executive summary., undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
    several versions
  - Nova Therapeutic Systems Inc. Business plan., 1997, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    two separate plans
  - Patents for "Radiation therapy and radiation surgery treatment system and methods of use of same" (the Cobalt Scalpel)., 1996-2000 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Patent #5,537,452, granted 7/16/1996; Patent #5,748,700, granted 5/5/1998; Patent #5,815,547, granted 9/29/1998; Patent #5,894,503, granted 4/13/1999, Patent #6,104,779, granted 8/15/2000
    inventors named are Joseph S. Shepherd and Robert W. Rand [see pp. 11-12 of the 2000 Business Plan, Box 1, Folder 28]
  - Texts describing The Cobalt Scalpel., undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
    two typed manuscripts: one short, non-technical, and one longer, more technical and specific
  - Visual presentations of The Cobalt Scalpel., undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
    photocopies of 13 text slides; photocopies of 84 Power Point screens
  - Rand Neuropledgets for brain protection., undated; sealed packet, 3 photographs (Box 3, Folder 32)
    small, flat, paddle-shaped surgical sponges, patented by Dr. Rand in 1977 (U.S. Patents nos. D242,954 and 3,825,007); photos illustrating various sizes of the product
  - Law offices of Lyon & Lyon., 1998-2000 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    letters, invoices, and Power of Attorney document
    attorneys for U.S. patents
  - Trainor & Robertson, Attorneys at Law., 1999 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    correspondence and lease agreements
  - Goren, Marcus, Masino & Jacobs, Certified Public Accountants., 2001 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Power of Attorney for tax issues
  - Miscellaneous corporate documents and correspondence., 1999-2004 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Materials for a Novel or Screenplay., 2000-2003; Series 4.; 5 folders
  Plot outlines and text sketches; correspondence with writer/co-author; folders of scientific materials on stem cell research and Alzheimers Disease, perhaps for background research
  - "Neurogenesis - A Medical Thriller", by Robert W. Rand and Maida Sussman., 2000-2002 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    nine-page typed "treatment for a feature-length commercial film or a novel", by Rand; cover letter, a synopsis, and the first 15 pages of the manuscript sent to New York publisher Berkley Books/Penguin Putnam Inc.
  - Letters to co-author Maida Sussman., 2000-2003 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    suggestions for plot and dialog, explanations of medical procedures; Oct. 23, 2001 letter mentions ideas for a second book
  - Letters from co-author Maida Sussman., 2003 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    script pages and background information
  - Background material - stem cells., 2000 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    12-page typed extract from a review by J. S. Odorico, et al.; reprints and clippings on stem cell research and brain cell death and neurogenesis
  - Background material - Alzheimer disease, etc. (Box 3, Folder 41)
    reprints, clippings
- Carl Wheeler Rand, M.D., 1912-1940; Series 5.; 8 folders
  Diploma, certificates, some memorabilia, glass lantern slides including some in the RESTRICTED Series
  - Diploma., 1912 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Doctor of Medicine, The Johns Hopkins University
  - Certificate., 1920; carved and gilded wood frame (Box 6, Folder 4)
    certificate naming Dr. Carl Rand as a Fellow of the American College of Surgeons
  - Member, The Society of Neurological Surgeons., 1922; mounted on cardboard (Box 6, Folder 5)
    letter from the Society's Secretary, informing Dr. Carl Rand of his election
  - Board certificate., 1940 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Board certification in Neurological Surgery, The American Board of Neurological Surgery
  - Note from Harvey B. Cushing., 1926 June 19; items mounted on poster board (Box 6, Folder 7)
    black-edged note: "Thanks dear Carl for your message of sympathy. HC. June 19"; envelope; newspaper clipping: "Crash kills students and girls"
    Dr. Cushing's son William H. was one of the Yale students killed
  - Portrait of William H. Welch., undated; 15 x 24 cm photogravure, mounted on cardboard (Box 6, Folder 8)
    half-length, seated, wearing academic robe; facsimile autograph; seal of The Johns Hopkins University; artist: Doris U. Jaeger
  - "Studies in intracranial physiology & surgery: The third circulation; The hypophysis; The gliomas", by Harvey Cushing., 1926 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    volume bears Dr. Carl Rand's personal book plate
  - Ophthalmoscope., undated; instrument and box (Box 5, Folder Object 1)
    "Dr. Carl W. Rand" stamped on tape attached to box cover